我先问你一个问题
Let me ask you a question first
如果让你选一本书
If you had to pick one book
能让普通人的认知水平提高一个量级
That could level up an ordinary person's thinking by an order of magnitude
你会选哪本
Which one would you choose
很多人会说国富论资本论
Many people would say The Wealth of Nations or Das Kapital
但巴菲特自己开口推荐的
But Buffett personally recommended
是另一本
A different one
穷查理宝典
Poor Charlie's Almanack
这本书的作者
The author of this book
叫查理芒格
Is Charlie Munger
巴菲特的搭档
Buffett's partner
伯克希尔哈撒韦的副董事长
Vice Chairman of Berkshire Hathaway
99岁去世前
Right up until he passed away at 99
还在每天读书6小时
He was still reading 6 hours a day
在2023年的股东大会上
At the 2023 shareholders meeting
有人问芒格
Someone asked Munger
普通人最大的错误是什么
What is the biggest mistake ordinary people make
你猜他怎么答
Guess what he said
不是没钱
It's not being broke
不是没机会
It's not lacking opportunities
不是没人脉
It's not having no connections
他说
He said
是拿着锤子看什么都是钉子
It's seeing every problem as a nail when all you have is a hammer
什么意思
What does that mean
就是你只会一种思维方式
It means you only know one way of thinking
然后用它去解释这个世界上所有的问题
And you use it to explain every problem in the world
这是一个100亿美金身家的老头
This is the final advice from a man worth 10 billion dollars
留给我们的最后忠告
Left for the rest of us
今天我用10分钟
Today I'll use 10 minutes
把这本书最核心的3个思维工具讲给你听
To walk you through the 3 core thinking tools from this book
这3个工具
These 3 tools
你只要用上一个
If you put even one of them to use
未来10年的人生决策就会跟现在完全不一样
Your life decisions over the next 10 years will be completely different
回到芒格那句话
Back to what Munger said
拿着锤子看什么都是钉子
To the man with a hammer everything looks like a nail
这句话其实很扎心
This actually hits pretty hard
我给你看几个例子
Let me show you some examples
你看看像不像自己身边的人
See if they remind you of people you know
有个朋友
There's a friend
本科学心理学
Who studied psychology in college
不管你跟他聊什么
No matter what you talk about with them
经济不景气
The economy is bad
夫妻吵架
A couple fighting
孩子学习不好
A kid struggling in school
公司倒闭
A company going under
他都能给你绕到原生家庭上去
They'll twist it back to childhood family issues
这就是一把锤子
That's one hammer
还有一种朋友
Another type of friend
搞IT出身
From an IT background
不管你跟他聊什么
No matter what you bring up
他都给你画流程图
They'll draw you a flowchart
恋爱要画流程图
Dating needs a flowchart
养孩子要画流程图
Raising kids needs a flowchart
买菜要画流程图
Even grocery shopping needs a flowchart
这也是一把锤子
That's another hammer
最常见的一种
The most common type
是只懂金钱的人
Is someone who only understands money
什么事都换算成值多少钱
They convert everything into how much it's worth
时间值多少钱
How much is time worth
感情值多少钱
How much are feelings worth
健康值多少钱
How much is health worth
自由值多少钱
How much is freedom worth
一切都被定价
Everything gets a price tag
这同样是一把锤子
That's yet another hammer
芒格说
Munger said
绝大多数人的一生
Most people's entire lives
就死在自己唯一的那把锤子上
Die on their single hammer
为什么
Why
因为人脑的本能是省力
Because the brain's instinct is to save energy
学会一种思维方式
Learning one way of thinking
已经费了好大力气
Already takes a lot of effort
谁愿意为了解释一个新问题
Who wants to learn a whole new way of thinking
再去学一种新的思维方式
Just to explain a new problem
太累了
That's exhausting
所以大多数人这一辈子
So most people go through their whole lives
就用一两种思维去硬套所有问题
Force-fitting one or two mental models onto every problem
然后在该用经济学的时候用心理学
Using psychology when economics is called for
该用心理学的时候用法律
Using law when psychology is needed
该用统计学的时候用直觉
Going with gut feeling when statistics should apply
最后撞得头破血流
And end up crashing and burning
还以为是命不好
Blaming it on bad luck
你回头看看自己
Look back at yourself
你过去5年
Over the past 5 years
是不是也只用了两三把锤子
Haven't you also been using just two or three hammers
注意听
Listen carefully
这里讲一个让芒格成为芒格的核心方法
Here's the core method that made Munger who he was
它叫多元思维模型
It's called the latticework of mental models
什么意思
What does that mean
芒格说
Munger said
你脑子里至少要有100个思维模型
You need at least 100 mental models in your head
来自不同学科
From different disciplines
数学的
Mathematics
物理的
Physics
生物的
Biology
心理学的
Psychology
经济学的
Economics
历史的
History
化学的
Chemistry
不同领域
Different fields
不同视角
Different perspectives
互相补充
Complementing each other
遇到一个新问题
When you face a new problem
不是用唯一的那把锤子去敲
You don't just swing your one hammer
而是把这100个模型一个个拿出来比对
Instead you pull out these 100 models one by one and compare
这事儿
Which one of these
更像哪一个
Does this problem resemble the most
我给你举个芒格自己用过的例子
Let me give you an example Munger used himself
可口可乐为什么这么值钱
Why is Coca-Cola so valuable
如果只用经济学
If you only use economics
你会说是因为它有定价权
You'd say it's because of pricing power
有规模效应
And economies of scale
但芒格不是这么想的
But Munger didn't think that way
他用了4个学科的模型同时分析
He analyzed it using models from 4 disciplines at once
第一个
Number one
心理学的条件反射
Classical conditioning from psychology
红色罐子
The red can
开瓶气泡声
The fizz when you open it
冰凉口感
The cold refreshing taste
让人形成自动联想
Creates automatic associations in people's minds
第二个
Number two
生物学的进化偏好
Evolutionary preference from biology
人类天生喜欢甜和咖啡因
Humans are hardwired to love sugar and caffeine
这是基因写好的
It's coded into our genes
第三个
Number three
经济学的网络效应
Network effects from economics
可口可乐越普及
The more widespread Coca-Cola becomes
越多人模仿
The more people imitate it
全球都在喝
The whole world is drinking it
第四个
Number four
社会学的身份认同
Social identity from sociology
可乐变成一种美国生活方式的象征
Coke has become a symbol of the American lifestyle
4个模型叠在一起
Layer these 4 models together
他得出结论
And he reached his conclusion
这是一个跨越100年都很难被替代的资产
This is an asset that's nearly impossible to replace even over 100 years
然后他和巴菲特1988年重仓买入可口可乐
Then in 1988 he and Buffett went heavy on Coca-Cola stock
到现在赚了多少
How much have they made since
超过200亿美元
Over 20 billion dollars
你看
You see
多元思维模型不是装逼
A latticework of mental models isn't just showing off
是用它
With it
你能比别人看得更深
You can see deeper than others
更早
Earlier
更准
And more accurately
我再给你一个生活里的例子
Let me give you another real-life example
你身边有没有人
Do you know someone
谈了好几次恋爱都谈不下去
Who's had multiple relationships but none of them worked out
如果你只用心理学解释
If you only explain it with psychology
你说他原生家庭有问题
You'd say their family of origin is the issue
但芒格的方法是叠加多个学科
But Munger's approach is to layer multiple disciplines
经济学
Economics
他为这段关系投入的成本
How much they've invested in the relationship
是不是远低于对方
Is it far less than what the other person put in
沉没成本不平衡
Unbalanced sunk costs
社会学
Sociology
他的朋友圈和对方差距太大
Their social circles are too far apart
社会支持系统冲突
Conflict in social support systems
进化心理学
Evolutionary psychology
他可能在选择一个跟自己生育策略不匹配的对象
They might be choosing a partner who doesn't match their reproductive strategy
行为经济学
Behavioral economics
他每次决定都靠当下情绪
Every decision they make is driven by the emotion of the moment
没有用理性分析
No rational analysis involved
4个角度一叠加
Layer these 4 angles together
问题立刻立体
And the problem instantly becomes three-dimensional
解决方案也不再是单一的去做心理咨询
The solution is no longer just going to therapy
而是从4个层面同时调整
But adjusting on all 4 fronts at the same time
这就是多元思维模型的威力
That is the power of the latticework of mental models
它不是让你变得博学
It doesn't make you a know-it-all
是让你变得准确
It makes you accurate
回到主线
Back to the main topic
芒格在书里反复强调一个词
Munger repeatedly emphasizes one phrase in the book
倒过来想
Invert always
always invert
什么叫倒过来想
What does invert always mean
我给你看一个最经典的例子
Let me show you the most classic example
1985年
In 1985
可口可乐的CEO问芒格
The CEO of Coca-Cola asked Munger
怎么让可口可乐成为更伟大的公司
How to make Coca-Cola an even greater company
如果是你
If it were you
你会怎么答
How would you answer
大多数人会说
Most people would say
投更多广告
Spend more on advertising
研发新口味
Develop new flavors
扩张到更多国家
Expand to more countries
芒格反过来问
Munger flipped the question around
怎么样才能毁掉可口可乐
How could you destroy Coca-Cola
他列了10条
He listed 10 things
让它失去那种独一无二的口感
Lose that one-of-a-kind taste
让它的瓶装合作伙伴破产
Drive its bottling partners into bankruptcy
让它的品牌跟某种政治丑闻绑定
Tie the brand to some political scandal
让健康趋势对它不利但它不去应对
Let health trends turn against it without responding
让某次广告冒犯了某个种族群体
Have an ad offend some ethnic group
列完之后
After listing them all
他对CEO说
He told the CEO
把这10条做反
Do the opposite of all 10
你就找到了所有要避免的事
And you've found everything to avoid
剩下的
The rest
就是怎么不做这些事
Is simply not doing those things
这就是逆向思维
This is inversion thinking
它的核心是
The core idea is
不去想怎么成功
Don't think about how to succeed
而是想怎么必败
Think about how to guaranteed fail
然后避免必败的所有路径
Then avoid all the paths that lead to guaranteed failure
听起来很简单
Sounds simple right
但99%的人不会用
But 99% of people never use it
为什么
Why
因为人天生喜欢追求获得
Because humans are naturally wired to chase gains
讨厌思考失去
And hate thinking about losses
但你想想
But think about it
一个人这辈子能不能过得好
Whether a person lives a good life or not
最大的变量不是他抓住了多少机会
The biggest variable isn't how many opportunities they grabbed
是他避开了多少深坑
It's how many deep traps they avoided
我再给你一个活在你身边的例子
Let me give you another example from everyday life
普通人想怎么变富有
Ordinary people think about how to get rich
学投资
Study investing
学创业
Study startups
学副业
Study side hustles
学短视频
Study short videos
学了一堆
They learn all sorts of things
结果还是穷
And they're still broke
但芒格的方法是反过来
But Munger's approach flips it around
怎么必然变穷
How do you guaranteed go broke
第一
First
不停消费奢侈品打肿脸充胖子
Keep buying luxury goods to impress others beyond your means
第二
Second
把所有钱投到自己听不懂的东西上
Put all your money into things you don't understand
第三
Third
借钱赌博
Borrow money to gamble
借钱炒股
Borrow money to trade stocks
借钱买跌的资产
Borrow money to buy declining assets
第四
Fourth
从不存钱
Never save money
从不投资
Never invest
从不算账
Never track your spending
第五
Fifth
被人煽动情绪做决定
Let other people's emotions drive your decisions
这5条做反
Do the opposite of all 5
你就在变富的路上了
And you're already on the road to wealth
不需要什么高明策略
No brilliant strategy needed
不踩这5个坑
Just avoid these 5 traps
已经赢过90%的人
And you're already ahead of 90% of people
倒过来想
Invert always
always invert
请你把这2个英文单词记一辈子
Please remember these 2 English words for the rest of your life
最后一个工具
The last tool
叫能力圈
Is called the circle of competence
什么意思
What does that mean
芒格说
Munger said
每个人都有一个自己真正擅长的领域
Everyone has a field they're truly good at
这个领域很小
This field is very small
可能就是你工作了10年的那个细分行业
It might be the niche industry you've worked in for 10 years
可能就是你研究了20年的那个游戏品类
Or the game genre you've studied for 20 years
可能就是你养育了2个孩子之后才懂的那一套教育方法
Or the parenting methods you only understood after raising 2 kids
这个小小的圈子
This small circle
叫你的能力圈
Is your circle of competence
在能力圈里面
Inside your circle of competence
你的判断比90%的人准
Your judgment is better than 90% of people
在能力圈外面
Outside your circle of competence
你跟瞎猜没区别
You're basically guessing blind
但人最大的悲剧是什么
But the biggest human tragedy is
在能力圈外面
Placing your biggest bets
赌注下得最大
Outside your circle of competence
你看那些破产的中产
Look at those bankrupt middle-class families
不是因为本职工作不行
It's not because their day job failed
是因为他在自己根本不懂的股票
It's because they went all in on stocks
币圈
Crypto
海外房产
Overseas real estate
复杂理财上下了重注
And complex financial products they knew nothing about
赔的不是几万
They didn't lose just tens of thousands
几十万
Or hundreds of thousands
是几百万
They lost millions
而本职工作上的那些经验
Yet all that experience and insight from their actual job
那些洞察
All those insights
他根本不愿意用来变现
They had no interest in monetizing
巴菲特从不投科技股
Buffett never invested in tech stocks
几十年
For decades
他不是看不起科技
Not because he looked down on tech
他自己说
He said it himself
科技不在我的能力圈里
Tech is outside my circle of competence
直到苹果他研究透了
Until he thoroughly studied Apple
他才进
Only then did he get in
一进就是2000亿美元
And he went in with 200 billion dollars
你比一下你自己
Compare that to yourself
过去你赚的钱里
Of all the money you've made
有多少是在能力圈里赚的
How much was earned inside your circle of competence
亏的钱里
And of all the money you've lost
有多少是在能力圈外亏的
How much was lost outside your circle of competence
我猜你心里已经有答案了
I bet you already know the answer
我给你模拟一个场景
Let me paint you a scenario
你是个做了10年新媒体的运营
You're a digital media operator with 10 years of experience
身边的人都在炒比特币
Everyone around you is trading Bitcoin
炒美股
Trading US stocks
炒AI概念股
Trading AI concept stocks
每次饭局都有人问你
At every dinner someone asks you
你不上车
Aren't you getting in on this
错过几个亿啊
You're missing out on billions
这时候你该怎么办
What should you do right now
用能力圈检验
Test it against your circle of competence
比特币
Bitcoin
美股
US stocks
AI概念股
AI concept stocks
你真的看得懂吗
Do you really understand them
不懂
No you don't
那就是能力圈外
Then it's outside your circle
你的能力圈在哪
Where is your circle of competence
在新媒体
In digital media
你比99%的人懂流量
You understand traffic better than 99% of people
懂用户
You understand users
懂转化
You understand conversion
那你应该把钱
So where should you put your money
把时间
Your time
把精力投在哪
Your energy
投在能让你能力圈变现的事情上
Into things that let your circle of competence pay off
比如你自己起一个号
Like starting your own account
做一个MCN
Building an MCN
办一个新媒体培训课
Running a digital media training course
ROI比你瞎跟风的100倍都不止
The ROI would be over 100 times better than blindly following trends
巴菲特芒格几十年回报年化20%
Buffett and Munger averaged 20% annual returns for decades
靠的不是天赋
It wasn't talent
靠的就是死守能力圈这一条规矩
It was strictly staying within their circle of competence
其实关于这本书
Actually about this book
最核心的真相只有一句
The most essential truth comes down to one sentence
普通人和聪明人之间最大的差距
The biggest gap between ordinary people and smart people
不是智商
Isn't IQ
是思维工具的多少
It's the number of thinking tools you have
聪明人脑子里有100个模型
Smart people have 100 models in their head
遇到问题挑最合适的用
And pick the right one for each problem
普通人脑子里只有1个模型
Ordinary people only have 1 model
所有问题都用它套
And force-fit it onto every problem
差距
The gap
就在这
Is right there
最后送你一句话
One last thing for you
你想得越简单
The simpler you think
世界就给你越复杂的回应
The more complicated the world responds
你想得越多元
The more diverse your thinking
世界就在你眼前慢慢展开
The more the world unfolds before your eyes
如果今天这条视频对你有启发
If today's video inspired you
点个关注
Hit that follow button
我每周讲一个经济学故事
I share one economics story every week
帮你看穿那些每天都在踩
To help you see through the mental traps
却从来没注意到的思维陷阱
That you step into every day without even noticing
下一期
Next time
我们聊一个所有人都在焦虑的话题
We'll talk about a topic that's making everyone anxious
AI替你工作8小时
AI does your job for 8 hours
你的工资到底是该涨
Should your salary go up
还是该跌
Or should it go down
历史上每一次技术革命
Every technological revolution in history
都给出了同一个答案
Has given the same answer
但99%的人
But 99% of people
都猜错了方向
Guessed the direction wrong
我们下期见
See you next time